Guide to the Thomas Beer Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Thomas Beer Collection
1919-1947
YCAL MSS 389
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.2
(3 boxes) + 1 painting
The Thomas Beer Collection contains correspondence between Beer and his publisher Alfred A. Knopf and printed versions of Beer's writings. The Collection also contains reviews of Beer's writings, articles about Beer, original illustrations for Beer's publications, and a photograph of Beer.
Beer, Thomas, 1889-1940
Fuller, Arthur D. (Arthur Davenport), 1889-1966
Ward, E. F. (Edmund Franklin), 1892-1990
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source unknown.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Additional material about and by Beer can be found in the Beer Family Papers (MS 73) at Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University.
Thomas Beer (1889-1940)
Thomas Beer was an author of short stories, novels, and non-fiction prose. Beer was born in Council Bluffs, Iowa, on November 22, 1889, and raised in Yonkers, New York. He attended Yale University from which he graduated in 1911. Beer enlisted in the U.S. Army and served in France at the end of World War I. Between 1917 and 1936 Beer published a number of short stories in The Saturday Evening Post, and while his short stories provided him with financial security, Beer was more interested in his other writing projects. Beer's novels include The Fair Rewards (1922), Sandoval (1924), and The Road to Heaven (1928). Beer is also known for his non-fiction writings such as The Mauve Decade: American Life at the End of the Nineteenth Century (1926), Hanna (1929), which is a biography of Mark Hanna, and Stephen Crane: A Study in American Letters (1923). While on the surface Beer appeared successful, his personal life and writing career were troubled. While Stephen Crane was a critical success and was lauded as an important resource about Stephen Crane when it was initially published, it is now believed that Beer based the biography on forgeries of his own devising and portrayed a number of fictional events and people. In 1938 Beer suffered a nervous breakdown for which he was briefly institutionalized, and on April 18, 1940, died of a heart attack (although it's believed his death may have been a suicide) in New York.
Scope and Contents
The Thomas Beer Collection contains Beer's correspondence with his publisher Alfred Knopf and printed versions of Beer's writings. Also present are reviews of Beer's writings, articles about Beer, illustrations by Arthur D. Fuller and E. F. Ward used in Beer's publications, and a photograph of Beer.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1921-1929; II. Writings, 1920-1947; and Other Papers, 1919-1936.
Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Drawings (visual works) -- United States -- 20th Century; Paintings (visual works) -- United States -- 20th Century; Photographs -- United States -- 20th Century; Beer, Thomas, 1889-1940; Fuller, Arthur D. (Arthur Davenport), 1889-1966; Knopf, Alfred A., 1892-1984; Ward, E. F. (Edmund Franklin), 1892-1990
- Correspondence, 1921-1929; Series I; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains personal and professional correspondence dating from 1921 to 1929 and pertains to Beer's writing career.
  - Boyd, Madeleine, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Knopf, Alfred A., 1921-1929, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Writings, 1920-1947; Series II
  The series is organized into two subseries: Writings by Thomas Beer and Writings About Thomas Beer. Beer's writings are arranged alphabetically by title.
  The series contains published versions of Beer's writings and reviews of his work.
  - Writings by Thomas Beer
    - "Civilized Thought," The Saturday Review of Literature, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Fire Feathers," The Saturday Review of Literature, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Frank Swinnerton," The Bookman, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Letter to the Editor regarding Stephen Crane, The Saturday Review of Literature, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "The Mauve Decade: An Essay", undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Notes on Megalopolis" review of Young Men in Love by Michael Arlen for The Saturday Review of Literature, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Our Literature and the Gilded Age Theory" review of The Great Modern American Short Stories by William Dean Howells for The Saturday Review of Literature, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "The Princess Far Away," The Saturday Review of Literature, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Sandoval," The Saturday Evening Post, 1925 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 19)
  - Writings about Thomas Beer
    - Reviews of The Fair Rewards, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Reviews of The Mauve Decade, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Review of Mrs. Egg and Other Americans, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Reviews of Sandoval, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Reviews of Stephen Crane, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - "The Literary Spotlight: Thomas Beer" with a caricature by William Gropper, The Bookman, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - The Work of Thomas Beer: Appraisal and Bibliography by Evans Burnham Harrington, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - "Thomas Beer, Visits London, Tells Stories," Chicago Daily Tribune, 1929 June 1 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 20)
- Other Papers, 1919-1936; Series III
  The series contains illustrations for Beer's writings and a photograph of Thomas Beer.
  - Photograph of Thomas Beer, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Illustrations by Robert Staples for Beer's "Go Dine Your Enemy" and "I've Got Rings on My Fingers and Bells on My Toes", 1936 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 21)
  - Illustrations by E. F. Ward for Beer's "Lorena," in Saturday Evening Post, 1919 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 22-23)
  - Illustration by Arthur D. Fuller for Beer's "The Rope", circa 1922 (Box 4 (Art))